早上好 礼物 早上还不错
Good morning. Present. Morning actually been good.
好了 好了 从你早上的事开始 你说了什么建筑的事吗
Okay, great. So since your morning, what's uh, talk about building stuff?
呃 那么
Uh, so
的事情 嗯 这就是
things that, UH? So this is just to
给出了一些我认为非常有价值的不同类别的想法
kind of give a few different categories of ideas that I think are really worthwhile
让人们开始建设 开始真正具体的工作 就像 现在
for people to start building and to start, like, really concretely working on, like, right now.
总的来说 我认为 在加密领域 在以太坊 特别是在开发领域 在过去两年发生了很多变化
And so in general, I think, like a lot of things have changed in the crypto space and in the ethereum and of development world in particular, in the last two years.
就像很多技术一样 就像两年前的想法 想法和理论 在过去的几年里慢慢变成了现实
Like a lot of technology is that were like, really just like thoughts and ideas and theories two years ago have like, slowly become very real over the last couple of years.
在最近的一些声音中 比如 我已经谈到了其中的一些变化 对吧
And in a few voices recently, like, I've talked about what some of those changes are, right?
看 一个事实是 你知道 我们有了滚动装置 我们有了扩展 东西又变得便宜了 所以很多应用比一两年前更经济可行
Look, one is the fact that, you know, we have roll ups, we have scaling, things are getting cheaper again, so a lot of applications are just much more economically viable than they were one or two years ago.
所以 你知道 以前 你甚至可能会说 嗯 也许defy是唯一有意义的东西 因为defy是唯一人们愿意支付的东西 比如 每笔交易12美元
And so, you know, when before, like, you might even say, well, maybe defy is the only thing that makes sense to build, because defy is the only thing where people are willing to pay, like, $12 a transaction.
现在 你知道 交易的成本远低于12美元 而预收券每天都在改进
Well, now, you know, transactions are cost much less than $12, and roll ups are getting better every day.
你还可以建造很多其他的东西 对吧
So there's a lot of other things that you can build as well, right?
过去五年里发生的另一件非常重要的大事是零知识技术的发展
Another really big and really important thing that's been happening over the last five years is the growth of a zero knowledge technology.
对吧 所以 我实际上认为ZK的讽刺可能 就像 你知道的 对隐私 开放 自由 一种替代的 去中心化的网络技术运动来说 几乎是一样重要的 就像区块链一样 它们实际上是非常强大的工具
Right? So, like, I actually think that ZK snarks might be, like, almost even equally as important to the kind of, you know, privacy, openness, you know, freedom, kind of alternative, decentralized web tech movements as blockchains are like, they're actually extremely powerful tools.
它们非常有效地保护了我们的隐私 提供了我们的可扩展性 同时也保证了安全 这与区块链试图做的事情类似 对吧
They're extremely, uh, effective at giving us privacy and giving us scalability and and at the same time a pres uh, preserving security, which is a similar thing to what blockchains are trying to do, right?
在某些方面 像零知识证明和区块链实际上是彼此非常好的赞美 对吧
And in some ways, like zero knowledge proofs and blockchains are actually very good compliments for each other, right?
因为区块链给了你很多安全保障 但作为交换 它们牺牲了隐私和技能
Because blockchains give you a lot of security, but in exchange, they sacrifice privacy and they sacrifice skillability.
Zikisnarks还给了你隐私 也还给了你可扩展性
Ziki snarks give you back privacy, and they can give you back scalability.
嗯 所以开发寨卡病毒应用程序 对吧
Um? So build Zika apps, right?
基本上 我认为我们现在已经到了这样的地步 用于构建ziki暗应用程序的YAT工具每年都在变得越来越好
Basically, I think we've now gotten to the point where the YAT tools for building of what are ziki's dark applications are just getting better and better every year.
协议变得越来越好
The protocols are getting better and better.
我们证明这类东西的能力可以让你在合理的时间内在电脑上证明
Our ability to prove the like make proofs that you can actually prove on a computer in a reasonable amount of time.
随着我变得越来越好 我记得在2016年 当zCash的第一个版本发布时 生成一个签名需要超过1分钟
As I getting better and better, I remember in 2016, when the 1st version of z Cash launched, it took like, more than 1 min to generate a signature.
今天 就像所有这些应用一样 它们可以在某个地方生成证明 有时是3s 有时是小于1s 这取决于 呃 你知道 你使用的技术
And today, like all of these applications, they can generate proofs in like somewhere, sometimes 3 s, sometimes like less than 1 s, depending on, uh, you know, what technology you're using.
因此构建了您的知识应用程序 零知识应用 我认为 在隐私和可扩展性方面都很好
So builds your knowledge applications. Um, zero knowledge applications are, I think, a great for both privacy and a scalability.
嗯 对的 所以我在这里 我 我有这个链接到一个 对 帖子的链接
Um, right. So I'm here, like, I-I have this a link to a, yeah, block post.
如果你 g 如果你去VITELLOK 点c
If you just, uh, g, if you just go to VITELLOK, dot c.
A  或者如果它 或者它是一个wiki点 如果 嗯 点链接 嗯 任何一个 我的意思是 你只是向下滚动列表 嗯 我 嗯 大概一两个月前写了这篇文章
A., or if it, or if it's a wiki dot, if, uh, dot link, uh, either one, I mean, and you just like scrolled down the list, um, I uh, wrote this post about one or two months ago.
或者只是谈谈你可以用来作为知识证明的一些方法 来实际构建 呃 多种应用程序 呃 保护隐私
Or just talk about some of the ways that you can use as your knowledge proofs, uh, to actually build, uh, many kinds of applications that, uh, preserve privacy.
还有很多关于可扩展性的知识组应用 对吧
And there's also a lot of applications of of your knowledge groups for scalability, right?
z-k集合是一个很好的例子 这里有很多团队建筑 z英雄集合是EVM的 我认为这很好
So Z-K rollups are a great example, and there's a bunch of teams buildings, z hero ups for the EVM, which I think is great.
嗯 我认为 实际上 隐私还是比可扩展性探索得少一些
Um, privacy, I think, is still a bit less explored than, uh, scalability, actually.
就像一些有趣的隐私保护应用程序的例子 这可能是有意义的 嗯 隐私保护 比如 人性的证明 或隐私保护的证明
So, just like some interesting examples of privacy preserving applications that might make sense to work on, UM, privacy preserving, like, proof of humanity, or privacy preserving proof of pope.
就像 基本上 就像在以太坊 我们有 我们开始有 像 越来越多的这些协议 它们基本上是在一个站发布 像 嗯 在不同的 像 特定的地址 说一些关于控制该地址的人的事情 对吗
Like, basically, like in Ethereum, we have, we're, we're starting to have, like, more and more of these protocols, where they're basically issuing, like, some kind of at a station to d, like, um, at different, like, specific addresses to say something about the person who controls that address, right?
所以人性证明协议 比如
So the Proof of Humanity protocol, e.g.
这是一种协议 如果你必须注册 然后会有一个认证程序来验证提交的内容 如果它接受你 那么它基本上会说 这个地址对应某个独特的人类
it's a protocol um where if you you have to sign up, and there's like a dow that verifies submissions, and if it accepts you, then it basically says like, this address corresponds to some unique human
对吧 这并不是说一个人拥有5000个账户
right? So it's not about, it's not like one person having 5000 accounts.
就像一个特定的人拥有一个账户
It's like one specific person that has one account.
如果你这样做了 如果你有完美的人性作为一个成分 那么 像y 你就可以开始构建很多更强大的应用程序
And if you do, if you have perfect humanity as an ingredient, then, like y, you can start building a lot more powerful applications.
你有很多很多的空间来决定 比如 你要做什么样的东西 对吧
You have, like, a lot of, a lot more room to decide, like, what kinds of things you'll be building, right?
所以 例如 你可以建立一个空投 而不是做一个空投 只是基于
So, e.g. you could build an airdrop, where, instead of, like, doing an airdrop, just based
关于 嗯 你知道 比如 某人有多少硬币 某人发送了多少交易 你可以这样说 我实际上要给每个人15个硬币 对吗
on, um, you know, how, like, how many coins does someone have, how many transactions have someone sent, you can like, say, I'm going to actually give like, 15 coins to every single human, right?
嗯 你知道 你可以做 甚至n
Um, you know, you could do, like, even n.
以一种更公平的方式进行销售
f. T. sales in a way that's more fair.
嗯 你可以做销售 只是建立一个市场机制 试着在某种程度上 对个人更公平 嗯 我稍后会讲到这个
Um, you can do sale a, just create market mechanisms that try to be, like, more fair to individual people in some way, um, I'll talk about this later.
但是 也有一些方法可以让去中心化的治理更加公平 如果你试着 比如 数人而不是数硬币和隐私
But, like, there's also, um, ways to make, uh, decentralized governance more fair, if you try to, like, count humans instead of just counting coins and privacy.
保存着珀普的证据 所以 POPE 即出勤证明协议 是一种协议 比如 基本上 假设这个地址属于某个真正参加过某些活动的人
Preserving proof of Pope. So POPE, the proof of Attendance Protocol, is a protocol that, like, basically, let's you say this address belongs to someone who actually participated at some events.
对吧 我去年去阿根廷参加了一个会议 我得到了教皇的支持 对吧
Right? So, like, I went to, you know, a conferency in Argentina last year, and I got a pope for it, right?
所以有一个教皇被分发给每个在阿根廷参加会议的人
So there is a pope that that that got given out to everyone who visited this conference in Argentine.
所以你不仅知道这个人是人类 而且你实际上知道 比如 他们属于什么样的群体
And so you don't just know that this person is a human, but you you actually know, like, what kind of communities they're part of.
他们参与了多少不同的社区
And, like, what a diff no how much have they participated in, like, in different kinds of communities, right?
所以你会得到更多这类信息
So you get more of this kind of information.
这两种协议的最大挑战之一就是隐私 对吧
Now, one of the big challenges with both of these protocols is privacy, right?
你基本上是在向所有能看懂的人透露你是谁
Like, you're basically revealing to the anyone who can read the blockchain, like, who you are.
这是一个很大的隐私风险
And this is a big privacy risk.
但与此同时 我认为我们可以从这些协议中获得很多非常重要的东西
But at the same time, like, I think there's a lot of of really important things that we can gain from having these protocols.
所以我们面临的挑战是 如何在不付出成本的情况下获得收益
And so the challenge is like, how do we get the benefits without the costs?
对吧 零知识证明其实很有用 对吧
Right? And zero knowledge proofs could actually help a lot here, right?
比如 用你的知识证明 你可以做一些事情 比如证明你是一个独特的人 而不透露你是哪一个人
Like, with your knowledge proofs, you could do something like prove that you are a unique human without revealing which human you are.
你可以证明你有个教皇而且你参加了某个名单上的五场活动 而不用透露你参加了哪些活动 具体参加了哪些活动 也不用透露你的真实身份
You could prove that you have a pope and that you attended like, five events from a particular list, without revealing, like, which events you attend, specifically attended, and without revealing, like, what your actual identity is.
有很多有趣的应用
So a lot of interesting applications there.
负声誉 呃 这实际上是我在这篇文章里写的一个比较高级的苹果例子
Um Z-K Negative reputation. Uh. So this is actually one of the sort of more advanced Apple um examples in this post that I wrote.
基本上 这个想法是要有一个声誉系统 你可以在车站不仅做积极的 也做消极的
Basically, the idea is to have a reputation system where you can make at the stations that are not just positive, but also negative.
嗯 所以你可以证明一些事情 比如 你知道 我有 比如 我参加了一个去中心化的社交媒体平台 我发布了这些帖子 它们被上传 但我没有 但我也没有被下载 或者 我也没有 没有 没有被标记为虐待
Um, so you'll be able to prove things like, you know, I have, like, I participated in some decentralized social media platform, and I made these posts, they got uploaded, but I did not, but I also did not get downloaded, or, like, I also did not, like, have, did not get flagged for abuse.
所以你可以做所有这些事情 但同时也可以保护人们的隐私 对吗
So you can do, like, all of these things, but at the same time also preserve people's privacy, right?
你的知识和MPC数据是市场吗
Is your knowledge and MPC data marketplaces?
这很有趣 就像 我想很多人都对这个想法感兴趣 就像 为数据创造 像 更公平的市场声音
This is interesting, like, I think a lot of people have been interested in this idea of, like, creating, like, more fair market voices for data.
嗯 是的 你知道 这在医疗保健方面也有应用
Um. And, yeah, you know, there's applications of this in health care.
这在很多不同的空间都有应用
There is applications of this and, like, a lot of different spaces.
但问题是 这不仅仅是唤起问题 对吧
But there the problem is that, like, it's not just evocing problem, right?
因为你想要解决的是信任问题 但你想要解决的信任问题不仅仅是观看所解决的那种信任问题
Because you are trying to solve a trust problem, but the trust problem you're trying to solve is not just the kind of trust problem that of watching solves.
你也在试图解决隐私问题 对吧
You're also trying to solve a problem of privacy, right?
问题是 我想给出一点关于我自己的数据 但我不想给出更多的数据
A problem of, like, I wants to give a little thing about, a little piece of data about myself, but I don't want to give more data than that.
我的意思是 理想情况下 比如 你甚至想要提供数据 比如 某人是一个机器学习模型 而不是实际上 比如 直接给他们数据 对吗
I mean, ideally, like, you want to even give data that contributes to, like, say, someone's a machine learning model, without actually, like, giving them, giving them the data directly, right?
如果他想要做这些事情 那么你就需要一种不同的密码学叫做多人对抗多方计算
And if he wants to do those kinds of things, then you need a different kind of cryptography called multiplayer con multiparty computation.
所以结合你的知识证明和多方计算尝试创造更好的数据 市场声音
So combines your knowledge proofs and multiparty computation try to create better data, market voices.
我的意思是 这是一个非常高级的话题 但我认为这是一个前沿 你可以在这里建造很多令人兴奋的东西
I mean, this is a very advanced topic, but I think like this is the frontier, and there's a lot of exciting things that you can build here.
这些只是一些例子你可以把它们作为你的知识来构建
So those are just a few examples of things that you can build with as your knowledge stuff.
我是说 用你的知识来建造
I mean, I think building with your knowledge.
科技仍然 仍然是先进的 但是它变得越来越不先进 工具变得越来越容易使用
Tech is still, it is still advanced, but it's getting less and less advanced in the tools are becoming more accessible with every year.
所以我至少还是鼓励人们认真看待这次袭击 认真考虑 即使是现在
So I still minimum encourage people to really look at the attack and really consider, like, even now,
用它来建造一些东西一个灵魂绑定的符号
using using it to build something a soulbound tokens.
所以这
So this
是我写的几篇文章 一篇是我自己发表的 还有一篇是我一个月前和别人合著的论文
is, um, something that, um, a couple of um articles, one that I published myself, and A-A more recent paper that I co authored about a month ago.
基本上这个想法就是使用不可转让的代币 对吧
Like, basically the idea is of using tokens that are non transferable, right?
基本思想是
So the basic idea
是 你要有令牌代表 像 说 你实际上是一些社区的一员 你真的喜欢学习 喜欢 批准 你知道 你知道吗 你有经验 你证明了 嗯 你完成一些挑战 MM你想 像职业证明自己不同的事情 但是你想证明 像 其实你是一个人做这些事情 你不只是喜欢 从别人那里花50美元买一个代币
here is that, like, you want to be have tokens that represent, like, say, that you actually are of a member of some community, that you actually like learn, like, approve, that you know, that you know something, that you have some experience, you proved, um, that you completed some challenge, the MM You want to, like, pro prove different things about yourself, but you want to prove that, like, actually you were the one who did those things, and you did not just, like, buy a token from someone else for $50.
所以基本上是制造不可转让的代币
So basically making tokens that are like, non transferable.
蒲柏现在就是一个很好的例子
So Pope is actually a good example of this right now.
教皇代币是可以转让的 是ec07 20的 如果你想 你可以把它们送给别人 但你可以看区块链 看看这个教皇真的被转让了吗
Pope tokens, like, they are transferable in that, like, they are ec 07:20 ones, and you can send them to someone else if you want to, but you can look on the blockchain and see, like, has this pope actually been transferred?
嗯 如果你愿意 你可以把仍然住在原来地址的教皇和已经被转移的教皇区别对待 对吧
Um. And if you like, you can treat popes that are still in their original address and and popes that have been transferred, uh, differently, right?
嗯 我基本上期望这些东西会被用于很多 嗯 更多不同种类的项目
Um. And I'm basically expecting that these kinds of things are going to become used for a lot, m uh, like a lot more different kinds of, uh, projects.
我认为这有很多应用 对吧
So, and I think there are a lot of, um, applications of this, right?
我提到过一种 我们称之为灵魂药水
So one that I mentioned is, um, what we call soul drops.
所以我基本上是空投 为了获得空投的资格 就像你一样 你试着使用一些信息 比如链信息 来弄清楚 比如 你想要空投的社区里有谁 对吧
So I basically airdrops, where, in order to qualify for the airdrop, like you, you try to use some of this, like on chain information, to actually figure out, like, who is in the community that you want to airdrop to, right?
他们想要空投很多不同的项目 但他们总是面临的一个挑战是 如果你空投 那么有时候空投会被V-C处理 对吧
Like, a lot of different projects they wants to airdrop, but one of the challenges that they always face is like, if you airdrop, then sometimes the airdrop just gets farmed by V-C is, right?
V-C就是创建10万个账户
In V-C is just create a hundred thousand accounts.
有时候空投 你知道的 只是随便给别人
Sometimes the airdrop, you know, just give it to random people.
有人创造了一个非常高效的应用程序每个人都可以 在unic上交换他们的空投 只要32美元
And someone creates, like, a really efficient app where everyone can just, like, go and dump their airdrop on unic swap for 32 bucks.
每个人都这么做 你知道 你刚刚损失了很多钱
And everyone does that, and like, you know, you have just lost a lot of money.
所以你要做的是 我认为你要分配你的代币供应
So what you want to do is, like, I think you want to distribute your token supply.
你不会想要这种 你知道的 蓝色统治的反乌托邦 在那里 七个人和风投基金控制了一半的供应
You don't want to have this kind of, you know, bluetocratic dystopia, where, like, seven people and VC funds control half the supply.
但是你也想 像这样 把供应给你社区里的人 对吧
But you also want to, like, actually give the supply out to people who are actually in your community, right?
那么 你如何以一种非常可验证的 自动的方式 告诉你 它给了你 一些 你知道的 我们称之为可信的中立 一些能力 比如 向公众证明你分配它的方式是公平的 你不是 安静地给自己很多硬币
And so how do you tell, like, in a very verifiable, kind of automatic way, that it gives you, like, some of, you know, what we call credible neutrality, some ability to, like, actually prove to the public that you were fair in how you allocated it, and that you're not, like, quietly giving lots of coins to yourself.
单独绑定的代币实际上可能是一种非常强大的工具 对吧
Um, sole bound tokens might actually be a very powerful tool for doing this, right?
所以 人性的证明 你可以限制在个人身上
So, proof of humanity, you can, like, limit to individual people.
嗯 你甚至可以 你知道 用人性的证明做一些有趣的事情 比如你可以做一种公平的I-C-O 如果你想 比如说 卖掉f你可以花1美元买第一个代币 但是买第二个代币要花2美元 买第三个代币要花3美元
Um, you could even, like, you know, do interesting things with proof of humanity, like you could make a sort of fair I-C-O, where, if you want to, let's say, sell the f you could buy your 1st token for $1, but then buying your 2nd token cost $2, buying your 3rd token cost $3.
所以你买的代币越多 每个代币的价格就越高
And so the more tokens you buy, the higher the price of each one goes.
对吧 所以有不同的方法来创造这些机制 让它们 你知道的 少一些财阀 多一些公平
Right? So there's like, different ways to try to create these mechanisms, to sort of make them, you know, less plutocratic and more fair um.
人类存在的证据可能是其中重要的一部分
And things like proof of humanity could be a big part of it.
出勤证明协议可以很好 而且类似的想法不仅可以很好地检查 比如 谁是人类 而且可以检查 比如 谁是某个特定社区的实际成员
Proof of attendance protocol can be good and and similar ideas can can be good for not just checking, like, who is a human, but also checking, like, who is actually a member of a particular community.
嗯 我认为这里有很多很好的想法 但实际上还有很大的空间来建造基础设施 让做这些事情变得很容易
Um. And I think there's a lot of, like, good ideas here, but there is a lot of room still to actually build the infrastructure to make it really easy to do these kinds of things.
所以我认为 这对开发者来说是另一个挑战 比如尝试开发更多这样的工具
So I think this is, like, you know, another challenge for developers, like try to actually build more of these tools.
嗯 另一个有趣的是 呃 在这个概念中 像是 单独绑定的 token封闭的社区论坛 对吧
Um, another, um interesting one is, uh, in this concept of, like, solebound, token gated community forums, right?
所以 想象一下一个私人聊天 基本上聊天中说的东西 不会自动传播给所有人 但他们 你知道 不像只有几个人决定谁进谁出
So, like, imagine a private chat where basically things that are said in the chat, they don't get automatically broadcasted to everyone, but they, you know, it isn't like just a couple of people who decide who gets in and who gets kicked out.
相反 比方说 你有一个疑问 陶氏化学发行代币 甚至 基于一些衡量你是否在一个特定的社区 这决定了你是否能进入
Instead, like, say, you have a doubt, and that Dow issues tokens, and even, like, based on some measurement of whether or not you're in a particular community, that determines whether whether or not you can get in.
我的意思是 很明显 就像鞋底骨代币和零知识一样 我认为它们并不是分开的
So this, I mean, obviously, like sole bone tokens and zero knowledge, I think, like they're not separate.
它们之间有非常重要的协同作用
And I there are really important synergies between them.
我认为有协同效应的原因很明显 对吧
And the reason why there are really important synergies, I think, is obvious, right?
因为 有了这种能力 你可以做很多很酷的事情 比如 了解更多关于人们的事情
Because, like, there's a lot of really cool things that you can do just by having the ability to, like, know more things about the people
在你与之互动的地址后面 能够说 比如 这个人来自这个社区 这个人不是
behind the addresses that you're interacting with, and being able to say, like, this person is from this community, this person is not.
这个人是这个项目的和弦开发者
This person is a, you know, chords developer of of this project.
你知道 这个人 你知道 有一个地址理论 但实际上 他大部分时间都在参与一些完全独立的项目 比如
And, you know, this person has, you know, one theory of address, but actually he is, he's mostly involved in some completely separate project in like,
能够区分这些东西
being able to distinguish those things.
但你获得的这种能力越多 你就越会侵犯别人的隐私 对吧
But the more you gain that ability, the more you're, like, breaking people's privacy, right?
零知识是一种很好的方式 我会找回一些隐私
And zero knowledge is a great way to, I'll get some of that privacy back.
嗯 所以 世界卫生大会 另一个 你知道 这里有很多有趣的想法
Um. So, wha um. Another, you know, a lot of interesting ideas here.
嗯 更好的公共产品资金 这是我们过去两年一直在讨论的问题 对吧
Um, better public goods funding. This is something that I think we've been talking about for the last two years, right?
基本上 就像区块链一样 社区需要找到公共产品的方法
Um, basically that, like blockchain, communities need ways to find public goods.
公共产品对每个人都很重要 但在区块链社区尤其重要 因为波士顿社区是互联网社区
Public goods are important for everyone, but they're especially important in blockchain communities because Boston communities are Internet communities.
他们严重依赖开源软件 在互联网上编写的公共文档 人们进行翻译 所有的工作都是完全在公开环境下完成的 这是非常有价值的
They depend heavily on open source software, public documentation that gets written on the Internet, people making translations, just all kinds of work that's completely done in the open, and it's extremely valuable.
但没有什么好办法来收费 对吧
But there is not a good way to charge for it, right?
所以 更好的方式 比如 资助它 实际上使用 嗯 你知道 社区的资金池来支持这些事情 甚至支持公共产品 或者超越区块链的空间 是我认为现在非常重要的事情
So better ways of, like, funding it, and of like actually using, um, you know, community pools of funds to support those things, and even to support public goods either go beyond the blockchain space is something that I think is, like, really important to care about right now.
我们怎么做呢 二次融资很有趣
How can we do this? I mean, so quadratic funding is interesting.
吉特币团队在过去的两年里一直在做这些实验 这些二次融资
So the Gitcoin team has been doing these experiments for the last two years, these quadratic funding rounds.
刚开始的时候 他有25000美元的配对池 但基本上没人在乎
And at the beginning, it was like this thing where he had like a $25000 matching pool, and basically nobody cared about it.
但我认为 随着时间的推移 我们看到它真的在增长和膨胀 现在它是这么大 我知道 500万美元的东西 你会看到这些非常大的匹配池每隔几个月就会发生一次 我认为这很神奇
But I think over time, we've seen it like really grow and balloon, and now it's this big, I'm, you know, $5000000 thing, and you have just these really big matching pools that happen every you get every couple of months, which I think is amazing.
但是 仍然有机会改进二次融资 并试图使它的机制更好 使它更安全 你知道 抵御攻击 使它更保护隐私 以及所有这些事情 所以这是公共产品问题的一部分
But there is still, like, opportunities to improve quadratic funding and to try to make it the mechanism better, make it more um, you know, safe against attacks, make it more privacy preserving, and all of these things, So that this is one part of the public goods problem.
另一种看待公共产品问题的方法是从信用分配的角度来看待它 对吧
Another way to look at the public goods problem is to look at it from the perspective of, like, credit assignment, right?
嗯 假设有人发明了一些令人惊异的新闻你的知识证明协议 这个新的零知识证明协议 使它 比方说 便宜十倍规模ethereium辊ups和隐私的证据
Um. So let's say that someone invents some amazing news your knowledge proof protocol, and this new zero knowledge proof protocol is like, makes it, let's say, ten times cheaper to scale ethereium roll ups and to proof privacy.
现在它还有其他一些神奇的特性
UM And it has some other magic, amazing properties right now.
这是一项公益事业 一旦你做了这件事 它就公开了 它被发表了 它对每个人都有好处
This is a public good. It's something that, once you do it, it's in the open, it gets published, it benefits everyone.
它甚至不仅仅让以太坊社区受益
It doesn't even just benefit the ethereum community.
它对每个加密社区都有好处
It benefits, you know, every crypto community.
它甚至可以让很多主流应用受益 你知道 工业应用 政府应用
It goes like, it could even benefit, like, lots of mainstream, you know, industrial applications, lots of government applications.
它可以使公民社会的应用程序更加安全
It can make civil society more applications more secure.
所以这是一种公共产品
So it's a very public good.
但要问问题出在哪里 有一种方法 就是从这个问题上看问题 比如 谁应该得到学分
But one of the ways of, like, asking what the problem is, is to look at it from the problem of, like, well, who should get credit?
对吧 答案几乎从来不是最后一个人
Right? And the answer almost never is one person right on the end.
因为 听着 很容易就能分辨出谁是最后一英里的人 谁是负责的人 谁是真正发表文章的人 但是发布者是发表文章的人
Because, uh, look, it's easy to to kind of tell who is, like the last mile person, who is responsible, really, who is the guy who actually publishes, but the pers the person who publishes the thing.
就像 他没有发明或者 你知道 她没有在洞穴里发明这个想法 对吧
Like, he did not invent or, you know, she did not invent the idea in a cave, right?
比如 呃 红色 现有的工作 综合现有的工作 与人交谈 创造一个想法的版本 找到一个人打破这个想法的版本 修正它 创造一个更好的版本
Like the uh red? Existing work, synthesized existing work, talks to people, created one version of an idea, found someone who broke that version of an idea, fixed it, created a better version of the idea.
合作的过程总是存在的
There is always this collaborative process.
他们所建立的每一个想法本身也是建立在其他想法之上的
And each of the ideas that they built on are also ideas that themselves, you know, built on other, on other ideas.
就像 有一棵大树 就像 从哪里来的信用
And like, there is this big tree of, like, where the credit comes from.
所以有一件事要考虑的是 我认为人们很长一段时间以来一直在考虑 天意的问题 对吧
So one thing to think about is, like, people, I think, have for a long time been thinking about, like, the kind of the providence problem, right?
这就像区块链 供应链应用程序 人们在2015年到2017年谈论了很多 对吧
So this is, like, blockchain, supply chain applications, like, people talked a lot about this in 2015 to 2017, right?
就像 基本上 如果你有 嗯 比如 如果你买了一些产品 你怎么知道 比如 你知道 不同的部分实际上来自哪个国家
Like, basically, if you have, um, like, if you get some product, how do you tell, like, you know, which country the different parts actually came from?
你怎么判断什么是值得信任的
How do you tell, like, what's trustworthy?
你能不能在供应链的每一步都设置加密链接 检查它们 我检查它们在链上 等等
Can you, like, put cryptographic links at every step in the supply chain, check them on I check them on chain, and all of that?
比如 我们也可以为公共产品这样做 对吧
Like, we could do that for public goods as well, right?
我们可以试着 把引用的概念形式化 让它们加密 让它们更不敏感兼容
We could try to, like, take the concept of citations and and formalize it, make them cryptographic, make them more insensive compatible, have
一种关于他们的更丰富的信息 就像 有更多的信息可以被用来适当地补偿 几乎每个人
a kind of more this kind of richer information about them, and just like, have more information out there that could actually be used to properly compensate, sort of everyone
整个过程都是这样的 比如 为公共产品生产一些公共的N-F-ts
all along the chain of, like, actually producing some public, um N-F ts for public goods.
N-F-t-s对我来说一直是个很有挑战性的话题 因为 一方面 我认为N-F-s可能是一个非常棒的筹款工具 它们真的可以帮助筹集资金
Uh, so like, N-F-T-S have always been this sort of challenging topic for me, because, on the one hand, like, I think N-F ts could be like a really amazing fundraising tool, and they could really help and, like, raising money
为那些真正需要它的东西和那些没有其他商业模式的东西 对吧
for things that really need it and things that don't otherwise have business models, right?
他们已经这么做了
And they kind of already do.
有很多世界各地的艺术家 甚至像东南亚 非洲和拉丁美洲这样的地方的人们 都找到了一种方式 通过非功能性生态系统赚钱
There is like a lot of artists that are around the world, and even people in places like, you know, southeast Asia and Africa and Latin America that like, really do get included in have finds a way of, like, making revenue through the NFT ecosystem.
但另一方面 就像 NFTS  有时会变成一种荒唐的事情 即人们会创造出价值300万美元的猴子
But on the other end, like NFTS, can sometimes become this sort of ridiculous thing, where people, are, you creating $3000000 monkeys?
对吧 所以 对我来说 我想我的理想世界是这样的 我不想讨厌n个fts 我也不想不加批判地喜欢n个fts
Right? So, like, to me, like, I guess my ideal world is like, not, uh, like, I don't, I don't want to hate n fts, and I also don't want to uncritically like n Fts.
但是 就像 我想建立更好的和Fts 对吧
But so, like, I want to build better and Fts, right?
你知道 我想 如果我们可以 尝试找到一种方法 让n个非法交易对公共物品更有好处 对吧
And, you know, I want to, it would be nice if we can, like, try to find a way to kind of get and make n FTS benefit public goods more, right?
所以 或者 你知道 如果你生产一些 比如 一些 公共产品 嗯 然后 比如 我想办法如何销售一些
So, or, you know, if you produce some, like, some, uh, public good, um, and then, like, f find a way to how to sell some m.
f T 为它 和公共利益 就像 你知道 它可能是一些科学结果
f. T. for it, and the public good, like, you know, it could be some scientific result.
它可能是一件艺术品 也可能是一篇博客文章
It could be a work of art, um, it could be a blog post.
它可以是一种基本的想法 在人们想要参与的生态系统中找到创造它的方法
It could be an idea of basically find ways to kind of create it in a the ecosystem that people want to participate in.
嗯 嗯 与此同时 我们实际上要确保得到资金的人不只是那些处于产业链末端的非常耀眼和有名的人 而是要确保 整个知识供应链都能得到补偿
Um, but um. And we are, at the same time, like, you actually ensure that the people who get the funding aren't just kind of like very flashy and famous people at the end of the chain, but try to actually make sure that sort of, the entire, you know, intellectual supply chain gets compensated.
嗯 嗯 所以 我认为 有很多有趣的想法可以研究
Well, uh, so a lot of, like, I think, interesting ideas to work on there.
更好的戴尔管理 所以我认为道氏很好 很多人都在做达拉斯 但与此同时 道氏在管理上有很多问题 就像他们的管理一般 我认为要么是集中的 要么是可攻击的
Um, better Dell governance. So I think Dows are great, and lots of people are doing Dallas, but at the same time, like dows have a lot of problems in governance, like their governance is in general, I think it's like either centralized or attackable.
我们看到了很多 有时一些非常可怕的袭击
And like, we see a lot, sometimes some pretty scary attacks.
就像最近 有一个稳定的硬币被抽干了 因为有人购买了51%的代币供应 并进行了治理操作 抽干了所有的钱 就像一个闪光流 在一次交易中完成的
Like last I think very recently, there was like a stable coin that got drained because someone bought up 51% of the supply of the tokens and made a governance operation to drain all the money, and did that in like, a flash flow and in a single transaction.
诸如此类的事情 之所以会发生是因为由投币诱饵驱动的治理 从根本上来说是有问题的 对吧
And the like, these kinds of things, like they happen because coin bait driven governance is, like, fundamentally broken, right?
我已经写过很多次了
And I've written about this many times.
所以这是 你知道的 另一个帖子 对吧
So this is, like, you know, another post, right?
谈论这个问题 有很多方法可以在边际上改善它 但我认为最终你需要的是不受驱动的治理
Talk about this, and there are ways that you can improve it on the margin, but I think ultimately you need to have governance that is not going driven.
所以这也是像灵魂绑定代币 像人性的证明 像证明 你知道 社区成员身份的证明 需要用到的地方
And so this is also where things like Soulbound tokens, things like proof of humanity, things like proof, you know, proof of community membership, come in.
比如 我们需要有治理 它依赖于其他东西 而不仅仅是 你知道 像代币所有权
Like, we need to have governance that depends on things other than just, you know, to like, token ownership.
我们甚至需要摆脱这样一种想法 即道琼斯的目的是满足代币持有者的意愿 对吧
And we need to, like, even get away from this idea that the purpose of a dow is, like, fulfilling the will of the token holders, right?
还有其他利益相关者也很重要 所以其中一个方向是非币驱动的治理平台
There are other stakeholders that matter to So one of the directions to go is of non coin driven governance platforms.
我已经讲过 在一些地方如何做到这一点
And like I've talked about, like, ideas for how to do this in a couple of places.
但也有一个问题 比如 实际构建使用这些想法的陶氏治理工具 对吧
But there is also the the problem of, like, actually building Dow governance tools that use those ideas, right?
就像今天 每个人都用叉子叉化合物 因为有很多很好的工具使陶氏化学更容易操作
Like today, everyone forks compound, because there's just lots of really good tools that are make Dow is easy to operate.
如果你假设你投下一枚硬币 投下它的化合物 没有好的工具
If you assume that you're down a coin, voting down and for its compound, there aren't good tools.
如果你想以其他方式建立一个底层 如果你想以其他方式建立一个底层 你必须自己动手 对吧
If you want to build a down some other way, if you want to build a down some other way, you have to do things yourself, right?
就像 你知道 在上个世纪 你知道 我们没有人会因为买I-B-M或者
And it's like, you know, in the last century, you know, we had, like, nobody gets fired for buying I-B-M or or.
这里没有人会因为king化合物而被解雇 对吧
And here it's like, nobody gets fired for for king compound, right?
但我认为应该有更多的人因为使用复合材料而被解雇 更多的人应该因为尝试不同的东西而得到奖励
But I think more people should get fired for for working compound, and more people should get rewarded for, like, actually trying something different.
所以 你知道 我们必须建立那些工具 然后使它更容易
So, you know, we have to actually build those tools and then make it easier.
方向也是更好的交流平台 对吧
Direction too is better communication platforms, right?
比如 治理不仅仅是投票
Like, governance isn't just about voting.
投票是治理的最后一步
Voting is the last step in governance.
在此之前的步骤是 你如何真正创造想法 如何让我们同意这些想法 甚至如何随着时间的推移改进这些想法 如何在最终投票之前获得反馈 这样你就可以更好地找到一个让90%的社区成员满意的想法 而不是只让51%的社区成员满意
The steps that comes before is like, how do you actually create ideas, come to consent us on ideas, even, like, improve ideas over time, and, like, get feedback even before the final vote happens, so that, you know, you actually can, like, better, find an idea that makes, say, 90% of the community happy, instead of just making 51% of the community happy.
更好的交流平台 我的意思是 肯定有一些项目在尝试做这种去中心化治理沟通的事情
So better communication platforms. I mean, there definitely are projects that are trying to kind of do this decentralized governance communication thing.
我的意思是 激进交换的人 他们经常谈论波利斯 对吧
So, I mean, like Radical Exchange people, they talk a lot about Polis, right?
这是一个寻找想法的平台 不同的子社区 不同的子社区可以
It's this platform for and of finding ideas that different sub commun-, different sub communities that can can
达成一致 而在阿格里通 台湾真的很喜欢它
agree on. And in Argerytong from what Taiwan really likes it.
还有 还有 呃
And, and, uh, it
在那里经常被使用 这是一个很好的例子 你们可以看看
gets used a lot there. So that's one good example, but you can look at that.
但是我认为这里还有很多空间可以做更多的实验
And, but I think there's also room for, like, a lot more experiments here.
但是 你知道 总的来说 我认为 就像 需要更好的管理 美元需要更好的沟通
But, you know, in general, I think, like, dows need better governance, dollars need better communication.
所以 这里有很多事情要做
So, lots of things to do here.
这些只是一些想法
So those are just a few ideas.
我是说 还有很多想法
I mean, there's plenty more ideas
你可以尝试 但我认为 你知道 有很多非常有趣的方向可以去做
that you can try, but I think, you know, there's a lot of really interesting directions set to work on.
这个领域有很多非常令人兴奋的潜力 这些潜力在两年前是不存在的
There's a lot of very exciting potential in this space that exists now that did not exist two years ago.
但还有很多东西需要改进
But there's also still a lot of stuff that needs to be worked on.
你知道 我希望这里的人们能成为解决方案的一部分
And, you know, I hope that people here can be a part of the solution.